so let's say if you have a door
and if you apply a force
at these three locations
let's say at point a
b
and c
is it easier to push the door at a b or
c what would you say
you'll find that it's a lot easier to
push the door at position a
but it's very very difficult to push it
at position c
and even though the forces are the same
there is a quantity that's different
and that quantity is known as the torque
torque
is the force
times the moment arm or lever arm
in the case of position a
the moment arm is greater
than that of position b
and so it's easier to move the door at
position a than that position b because
you can produce
a greater torque
at point a
at point b to generate the same torque
requires
about twice the force
as in position a
so it's a lot harder to move the door at
the middle or even at the edge of the
door on the left side
now let's talk about the different ways
in which you could calculate the torque
so we're going to apply a force
that's perpendicular to the door
and let's say l is the distance
between where you apply the force
and the axis of rotation
and i want to distinguish that with r
the moment arm
the moment arm is the perpendicular
distance from the axis of rotation to
the line of action
the line of action is a line that's
parallel to the force
it extends from the force
so that perpendicular distance
is known as the moment arm
so the torque
is the force times the moment arm
it's also
any perpendicular force times l
but now what if there's an angle
how does the situation change
if we put an angle
between the force and the door
so let's say if we apply a force at this
position
let's say this is parallel to the door
so
we have an angle theta
how can we calculate the torque now
so first let's draw the line of action
of the force
so that's the line of action
and then draw a line that's
perpendicular to the line of action
from the axis of rotation
so this line right here
is the moment arm
now we said that l
is the distance between where we apply
the force
and the axis of rotation
so what i'm going to do is turn this
into a right triangle i'm going to draw
it separately
so this is r
this is l
and notice that these two
they form vertical angles so this must
be theta as well
so theta is right here
so l is the hypotenuse
and if we want to calculate r from l
notice that r is opposite to the angle
theta so we can say that r
is equal to l sine theta using sohcahtoa
if you're not sure how to get this
start with the sine theta
is equal to the opposite side which is r
divided by the hypotenuse which is
across the box that's l
and if you multiply both sides by l
then you can see that r
is l sine theta
so we know that the torque
is the product of the force
times the moment arm and in this example
the moment arm
is l sine theta
so the torque
is the force
times l which is the distance between
where you apply the force
and the axis of rotation
and then times sine theta where theta is
the acute angle
between
where the force is applied
and basically the door
so that's one way in which you can
calculate it another way is to view the
problem differently
so that same force
has
a parallel component
and a perpendicular component
and here's the angle theta
notice that theta is opposite to the
perpendicular component of the force
here's the right angle
so the perpendicular component
is f sine theta
now
even though we're applying the force in
this direction
this is the component of the force that
actually does the work
to turn the object in this direction
so therefore we can focus on just the
perpendicular component of the force
and then this is l
which is the same as r in this problem
so the torque is equal to the
perpendicular component of the force
times l
and the perpendicular component of the
force is f sine theta
so in the end the torque is just
f times l
times sine theta so you get the same
equation
as this one
so
now you have all the equations that you
need to calculate the torque acting on
an object
now there are some other things that we
need to talk about
so whenever a force
causes an object
to rotate
in a counterclockwise direction
that force
will create a positive torque
and if you have another force
that causes an object
to rotate in the clockwise direction
then the torque generated will be a
negative torque
so keep that in mind
so here's a question for you
so let's say this is the axis of
rotation
and we're going to apply
a 200 newton force
3 meters
away from the axis of rotation
and at the same time
we're going to apply
a 400 newton force
at a distance of 1.5 meters
from the axis of rotation
calculate the net torque
acting on this object
feel free to pause the video
first let's calculate the individual
torques
so torque 1
is going to be
f1
times r1
where f1 is 200 newtons
and r1 is 3 meters
so this is going to create a positive
torque
of 600 newtons times meters
so that's torque 1. it's going in
the positive counterclockwise direction
now what about torque2
torque 2 has a tendency to cause the
object to rotate clockwise
which means that it's going to be a
negative torque
so let's call this f2
so torque 2 is going to be f2
multiplied by
r2
and so that's going to be 400 newtons
times 1.5 meters
we're going to say it's negative 400
because it creates a negative torque
so 400
times 1.5 is
600. so torque 2 is negative 600 newtons
times meters
the net torque
is basically the sum
of the two torques
so the first one is positive 600 the
second one is negative 600 so the net
torque is zero
which means that the object is in
equilibrium
so it's not going to rotate clockwise or
counterclockwise
let's try another example
so here we have a propeller
that
can spin in this direction or
that direction or this direction
it could spin different ways
so first we're going to apply a force
of 300 newtons
at a distance
of let's say 4 meters
and then we're going to apply another
force
of 600 newtons
at a distance of
3 meters
and at an angle
of 60 degrees
and then there's going to be another
force which is directed here
and that's going to be a 500 newton
force
and it's at an angle of 50 degrees
so calculate the net torque of the
system and the distance let's say it's 5
meters
from the axis of
rotation so i'm going to call this f1
f2
and let's say this is f3
so the net torque
is the sum
of all three torques t1 t2
and t3
so t1 is going to be f1 times r1
t2 is f2 times r2
and t3 is f3 times r3
now torque 1
is going to cause the object to rotate
in the clockwise direction so that's
going to be a negative torque so it's
going to be negative 300
times four
torque two will cause the object to
rotate in the counterclockwise direction
so it's gonna be a positive torque
so it's 600
times three
and times sine
of thirty
i mean sixty not thirty
now keep in mind r two
is l two times sine theta
so l
is 3
and theta is 60.
so now let's multiply by f3 times r3
now f3 will cause the object to rotate
in the counterclockwise direction so
it's going to be a positive torque
f3 is 500 newtons
and r3 we're going to use
l3 sine theta
where l3 is 5
and theta is 50.
so it's going to be
times sine of 50.
so the net torque
is going to be t1 which is negative 300
times 4
so that's negative 1200
plus t2 which is 600
times 3
times sine of 60
which is
15 58.8
and then plus
500 times 5
times sine of 50
which is 19
15.1
so the net torque
is about positive
newtons times meters
so that's the net torque of the system
because it's positive
the object will rotate
in the counterclockwise direction
the concept of torque is very useful for
leverage
you can use a torque
to multiply
a force by adjusting the lever arm of a
simple machine
so the simple machine we're going to
focus on is
basically the seesaw
so let's say if you apply a downward
force
of 300 newtons
at a distance of six meters
from the fulcrum
so this is the axis of rotation
and let's say
this part is three meters long
what is the output force
that will be generated
on the right side
if you push the left side down with a
force of 300 newtons
at this location
so what you need to understand is that
the torque that's generated on this side
this is a positive torque
that's going to create another positive
torque on the right side
so the torques will be the same
so let's call this t1 and let's call
this t2 but keep in mind in this example
t1 is equal to t2
the force that you exert on this side
will continue to travel on that side
so t1 is going to be f1 times l1
where f1 is 300 and the level arm in
this example is 6 meters you can say r1
instead of l1 the result will be the
same so t1 is 1800 newtons times meters
now t2 is going to be the same it's
going to be f2 which is basically the
output force
multiplied by the lever arm so i'm going
to write it as f2 times l2
so t2 is still going to be 1800 newtons
times meters
and l2 is now 3 meters
so 1800
divided by 3
is 600 so the output force
will be 600 newtons
so notice that the output force it
doubled compared to the input force that
you applied to the machine
so you put in 300 newtons and you got an
output of 600 units
so therefore the mechanical advantage
of this system is two
because
the machine it doubled your force
mechanical advantage
is the ratio between the output force
and the input force
now granted this is an ideal situation
an actual machine might produce a force
of 580 590 it may not exactly be 600 but
theoretically that's what it should be
the ideal mechanical advantage of a
machine
is equal to
the input lever arm divided by the
output level arm
the input level arm is the level arm of
the input force which is f1
so that's 6 meters
the output level arm is associated with
the output force which is three meters
so six divided by three
will still give you a mechanical
advantage of two
so this is the ideal mechanical
advantage and this is the actual
mechanical advantage of the machine
now another
simple machine that can use leverage to
multiply forces
is the shovel so let's say if you're
digging up a pile of dirt
and you want to lift it up and move it
somewhere else
so you're going to use a shovel
to get the job done
so let's say this is the shovel you're
using
and let's say this is the axis of
rotation
so you're going to apply a force in this
direction
and an output force will be generated in
that direction
now let's say that the distance
between the axis of rotation and where
you apply the force
is one meter
and let's say the output level arm
is 0.1 meters
so if you apply a force
of 200 newtons
what output force will be generated
so in the last example we saw that t1
is equal to t2
the torque that you create
in this direction will be equal to the
torque that's created in that direction
around
the axis of rotation
now t1
is equal to f1 times l1
the input force
times the input level arm
and t2 is f2 times l2 which is the
output force
times the output lever
so the input force
is 200 newtons
the input lever arm is 1 meter
we're looking for the output force
and the output level arm is 0.1 meters
so it's 200 times 1 which is 200 divided
by 0.1
so the output force
is going to be 2 000
newtons
so notice that
the smaller force
is associated with the longer side
and the stronger force
is associated with the shorter side
now it works out this way
so that the torques are balanced the
torques have to be equal
so now that we have the output force
what is the mechanical advantage of this
simple machine
so the mechanical advantage is equal to
the output force
divided by the input force
so that's going to be 2 000 newtons
divided by 200 newtons
which is 10.
so that's the mechanical advantage
of this particular shovel
it increases your force by a factor of
that is of course if you apply the force
at the edge of the shovel
if you apply it at the middle of the
shovel
your mechanical advantage will be
reduced by two it's going to be half of
its current value so it's gonna be five
so your output force at this position
will be 200 times 5 or a thousand
newtons
but if you apply your input force at the
edge
then the mechanical advantage will
remain 10 and so your output force will
be 2000 units
so therefore if you're lifting something
with a shovel
you don't want to put your hands here
because you're not going to create
enough leverage to increase the force so
you're going to be working harder to
lift up stuff
but if you want to lift up something
heavy
with less effort you want to place your
hand
at the edge of the shovel
now granted you may have to push down a
longer distance
but still you can lift up something
with a smaller amount of force
the force that you have to apply will be
small
relative to the force that the machine
will generate for you which will be
large
you